Tamara Paula Temple

Webologist and Software Craftsperson

) +1-(415) 503-9241 \boxtimes tamouse@gmail.com \bigcirc www.tamouse.org \bigcirc tamouse \bigcirc tamouse

architecture, full-stack, backend, APIs,

frontend, low-level design, coding, de-

iQuery, React, Redux, GraphQL,

Ruby, JavaScript, Perl, C/C++, Shell,

Python 3, PHP, HTML5, CSS3,

Ansible, Chef, Puppet, Vagrant, Docker,

tools bundler, rake, webpack, babel, npm,

bugging, testing

SCSS/SASS, HAML

grunt, gulp, make

Travis CI, Circle CI

Apollo

Summary

Deeply experienced in software design and development methodologies, especially related to the disciplines of software quality, web applications, user experience, and team building.

engineering

web libraries

languages

dev ops

Skills

general software engineering, web development,

dev-ops, business analysis, consulting,

facilitating, teaching

Rails, Sinatra, Django, Flask, Laravel

frameworks

databases PostgreSQL, MySQL, SQLite, Mon-

goDB, Cassandra, Redis

servers nginx, unicorn, puma, Apache

testing Minitest, RSpec, Cucumber, Capybara, Guard, Jest, Enzyme, Mocha, Chai, Jas-

mine, Karma, Protractor

operating Linux, Mac OS X

systems

Methods Program architecture and design; User-/task-centered design; Test-/behaviour-driven development; Structured analysis, design, development, and testing; Process flow analysis, systems theory, cybernetics; Object-oriented analysis, design, programming, and testing; Agile development, scrum master; Continuous everything: integration, testing, deployment; Precision elicitation and

facilitation, communication for action

Education

1975-1980 Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, 3.2

 GP_{A}

Additional Structured analysis, design, programming and testing, System testing, Objected oriented analysis, design, programming and testing, Consulting and facilitating skills, Neuro-linguistic programming certified practitioner, Project management, Public speaking and presentation skills, You Don't Know JS with Kyle Simpson, Advanced JavaScript, Numerous courses through FrontendMasters.com on Angular, React, Webpack, others

Experience

2017-present API-drive Rubyist, React/GraphQL Maven, ReachLocal (Gannett), Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Implement modern APIs for the Kickerv product, and develop replacement Reaxt web client using GraphQL interface.

- work on the Kickserv product
- build robust APIs to enable modern web client applications for desktop and mobile to access backend data
- o migrate API to use GraphQL
- create a React web client using GraphQL to talk to the back end application
- fix defects in existing frontend software
- o work with other engineers to build common components

2001-Present Web Developer, Tamara Temple Web Development, Mendota Heights, Minnesota.

Freelance web design and development, including pro bono work for non-profits and individuals desiring a presence on the Web. Includes finding hosting space, development of information architecture, design layout of site, development and/or repurposing of content, and maintenance. Work in Perl, PHP, Ruby on Rails, JavaScript, jQuery, Backbone.JS, AngularJS, Node.js, React/Redux, CSS, Sass, MySQL, SQLite, Apache, Lighttpd, Linux, Mac OS X.

- User experience and User-centered design for interactive web sites
- Database design for dynamic web sites and applications
- Creation and developing on frameworks for generating static web sites
- Frameworks and infrastructure to implement business logic and web site features
- Environments and tools for development, testing, integration and deployment
- Teach and coach new developers
- O Volunteer mentor/coach/instructor for Rails.MN, RubyBridge, Twin Cities Rails hack night

2015-present **Volunteer, TA, Mentor**, Girl Develop It, Minneapolis Chapter, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Volunteer to help women learn web skills in HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Git, and publishing.

- Teaching Assistant in several classes
- Lead Tuesday "Toast and Tech" sessions to help people study and work on projects
- Teach various classes, including: "Stylin With Sass", "Falling in Love With Git"

2014-2017 Organizer, Rails.MN Beginners meetup, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Train people new to Ruby on Rails how to develop web applications using the Rails framework.

- Teach monthly classes
- Provide resources and support for students
- Maintain web resources

2016-2017 Contract Software Developer, Software for Good, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Provide software to enable clients to query a large datastore with natural language and return meaningful datasets.

- write anisble and shell scripts to deploy project to staging
- write training questions and entity extraction code
- write extraction, transfer, and load scripts for external data
- provide code review and expertise to other project members

2016-present Contract Software Developer, Bluewater, LLC, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Developing a service to provide Bluewater clients quick and easy franchise marketing direct mail, email, and other marketing campaign services.

- o architect external user contact intercepts to absorb into client's data collection in the Data Warehouse
- develop various features in Ruby on Rails and JavaScript

2013-present Contract Software Developer, Ackmann-Dickenson, Minneapolis, Minnesota.

Contract development in the areas of Rails and JavaScript on several A-D projects.

- Pro subscriptions and e-commerce in Brewtoad
- One-button recipe ordering in Brewtoad
- Customer Onboarding
- ${\color{orange} \circ}$ Micro-service architecture and implementation
- Angular SPA clients for MSA backend
- Massive and complex data analysis product
- O Data ETL middle layer to provide a massive speed-up for an e-commerce website

2012-2013 **Deployment Validation Lead**, Novu, LLC, St. Louis Park, Minnesota.

Ensure the quality, accuracy and timely delivery of web site features and software, establishing quality goals and program for planning, design and development of new features, and providing guidance and leadership in best practices for web application development under Ruby on Rails.

- Ensure web site features and external design are implemented as expected and intended
- Provide guidance during planning, design, and development to ensure testable and maintainable code
- Provide feedback to designers and developers on user experience, usability, accessibility and other aspects of the overall site's quality
- Create automated front-end integration and full-system testing suite based on Cucumber, Capybara and Watir-webdriver

2007-2008 Senior QA Engineer, Shopzilla, Inc., Los Angeles, California.

Sole software quality assurance engineer on business information engineering software providing testing, validation, automation, consulting, and quality leadership to development teams.

- Capturing business intelligence information from the website logs for upstream viewing for the health and financials of the company. Created test scripts and automation in Perl. Used Oracle 9i and 10g data bases.
- Service to provide a logging facility to record redirects (click-throughs) which is how the company obtains its revenue.
- Development of tools to provide testing capabilities in Java, Spring, Hibernate, Mason and Jython (Python) using Eclipse.
- Modeled in UML.
- Worked in an Agile/Scrum environment

2003-2006 Business Analyst, Hewlett-Packard, California.

Provide training and migration services for users from an old contract management system to a new system.

- review customer needs
- provide in-depth training
- provide migration analysis and services

• implement migration from legacy application to new system

1982-2001 Various, Hewlett-Packard, California.

Business and Technology Process Consulting, Senior Software Quality Engineering and Management, Senior Software Engineering, Business Analysis.

- Analyzed clients' business processes and matched them to processes for the new system; created process flowchart diagrams to communicate the processes to client users.
- Provided internal business and technical consulting to senior managers, middle managers and individual contributors to improve business processes and product market performance.
- Developed network and nodal management tools for HP-UX.
- Improved the quality assurance and testing processes for network software development.
- Led a team of software reliability engineers focusing on networking products.
- Provided quality assurance and testing for networking products.